今天的烤子鱼特别新鲜
The fish is very fresh today
你们别客气，多吃点
Eat up, enjoy yourself
不好意思，打扰你们吃饭
Sorry to interrupt your dinner
不要紧，我们过那边坐
Never mind, let's sit over there
怎么这样晚？
It's quite late
是啊，刚下班
I've just finished work
怎么称呼你
What should I call you?
叫我孙太太
You can call me Mrs. Suen
你呢？
And you?
我先生姓陈
My husband's name is Chan
- 决定了就给我电话 - 好的
Call me when you decide I will
有没有把号码抄下
Did you write down my number?
抄下了
Yes, I did
那好，我送你出去
Fine, I'll see you out
- 不用了 - 要的，大家上海人嘛
Don't trouble No trouble
那么就这样决定了
So it's agreed then
谢谢你，我先走了
Thank you very much, I should go
- 好的 - 再见
Fine Bye
慢走，再会
Take care, goodbye
请问这里是不是有房间出租？
You've a room to let?
真对不起，刚租给那位太太
Sorry, it's just been rented to that lady
谢谢你
Thanks
你几个人住？
How many of you?
我跟我太太两个人
Just me and my wife
你不妨到隔壁试试看
Why don't you try next door
隔壁有房间出租吗？
They've a vacant room too?
是，隔壁顾先生的儿子刚结婚
Yes, Mr.Koo's son got married
搬了出去
and removed out
房间也想找人租
His room's empty
谢谢你
Thank you
不客气，你尽管试试
You're too polite, Try asking them
谢谢
Thank you
来，这里
This way, come on
这个不是我们的
Not that room
怎么搞的，真麻烦
Wrong again
先靠墙放着，小心啊
Careful, against the wall there
小柜子靠在那边
The little cupboard over there
慢慢来
Be careful
小心，别碰坏别人的东西
Don't break anything
别压坏了收音机
Not on top of the radio
周先生
Mr.Chow
怎么家俱这样多？
You have a lot of stuff for a couple
- 这个柜不是我的 - 又搬错？
The wardrobe isn't mine, wrong again?
是不是隔壁的？
It does next door
那搬回去，搬回去
Okay, next door
这些鞋子不是我的，是不是拿错了
There aren't my shoes
我想是隔壁的，拿过去吧
They must go next door
真是巧，搬家都碰在一起
What a coincidence, moving in on same day
怎么没看见你先生？
Is Mr.Chan here?
公司有事派他出门了
He's working abroad
下礼拜才回来
He'll be back next week
那你该等他回来再搬嘛
You should have waited, then
搬家那么辛苦，你一个人应付得了吗？
It's too much for you on your own
- 我可以的 - 叫王妈帮忙
I can manage I'll ask Amah to help
别客气，孙太太，我自己行的
No need, I can manage
怎么回事？
What's going on?
小心那镜子
Mind that mirror
陈太太，你继续收拾好了
Mrs. Chan, I'll leave you to it
- 这些书不是我的 - 又错了？
Those books aren't mine Wrong again?
不要紧，先放下吧
Never mind, just leave them there
这个小心放，这些会砸烂的
Mind how you hang the mirror it's fragile
这些杂志是不是你的？
Are these magazines yours?
是的，我先生的
Yes, they're my husband's
你先生懂日文啊？
He reads Japanese?
懂一点，他老板是日本人
A little, his boss is Japanese
还没请教你贵姓？
How should I address you?
我先生姓陈
My husband's name is Chan
我姓周，我先回去了
My name's Chow... I'll leave you in peace
谢谢你周先生
Thank you, Mr.Chow
不客气
Don't mention it
我去叫陈太太
I'll ask Mrs. Chan...
陈太太，跟我们一起吃饭吧
Mrs. Chan, eat with us before you go
我不吃了，我赶时间，我得去机场
No thanks, I must dash to the airport
- 你先生回来了？ - 是的
Your husband's coming back? Yes
那我不耽误你了
Then I won't keep you
- 出去呀？ - 晚安
Going out? Yes
对不起，我迟了
Sorry, I'm late
王妈，快点倒酒
Amah, pour some beer
干杯
Cheers
- 周太太，尝一尝我们的上海家常菜 - 我自己来就行了
Mrs. Chow, try some Shanghai dishes
陈太太到哪里去了？
Where is Mrs. Chan to so late?
她去接飞机嘛，她先生回来了
Meeting here husband at the airport
怪不得打扮得那么漂亮
So that's why she looks different
我都帮你收拾好了，你自己小心点
It's all packed, take care on your trip
知道了
I will
你这回去好久吗？带那么多东西？
How long this time?
是呀，要一两个月
Two to four weeks
你记得回来的时候
Remember when you come back
带两个你上回送给我的皮包
Bring back two more of those handbags
谁要？
Who for?
我老板
Mr.Boss
两个那么多？
Two of them?
你知道啦
You know why
那要不要同颜色？
Different colours?
一样颜色行了，管它呢
The same will do? Who cares?
呐，可是你说的
Whatever
何太太吗？我是苏秘书呀
Mrs. Ho
何先生现在还在谈事情
Mr.Ho is still in a meeting
他说今晚会晚回家
He'll be home late
叫你们别等他吃饭
Please don't wait to eat
是啊，我们这阵子很忙
Yes, we're so busy at the moment
我请他忙完了给你打电话
Yes, I'll ask him to call you when he gets back
给我太太打过电话了？
Did you call my wife?
打过了，我说你会晚一点回去
Yes, I said you'd be back later
帮我订了位没有？
Have you booked the restaurant?
订了，八点两位
A table for two at eight
余小姐刚来电话，她说马上要出门
Miss Yu called to say
叫你快点
she's on her way
吃过饭我就回来
I'll be back after dinner
要不要带点东西给你吃
can I bring you something?
不客气，我自己出去吃就行了
No thanks, I'll get my own
如果你办完事情我还没回来
Leave when you're ready
你先走，我来锁门好了
I'll lock up
何先生，你走了？
Good evening, Mr.Ho Evening
- 陈太太，出去呀？ - 是的
Going out, Mrs. Chan Yes
这时候还要出去呀？
Going out so late?
我去买面
Just getting some noodles
王妈在弄蹄膀汤，大家一块吃
Amah is making pork soup, join us
别客气，我不是太饿，我想出去走走
Thanks, I'm not really hungry I just want some air
- 不要客气嘛 - 下次吧
You're too polite Next time
王妈，三哥他们都饿了，我们吃吧
They're all starving, we can eat
跟明哥说了没有？
Have you spoken to Ming?
那么我跟别人去
So I'll go with someone else
讲着玩的
Just kidding
我会早点下班，你也早点回来
I'll be early tonight, see you soon
- 再见 - 再见
Bye
阿周
Chow
来啦
Coming
周，下班了，东西留着明天做
Time to go, finish it tomorrow
做的差不多了，弄完再走了
No, I'm nearly there
明哥
Oh, Ming
- 我下个月想请几天假 - 干什么？
I need a few days off next month why?
答应跟太太去旅行，都说了好几年
I promised my wife a trip
你帮帮我
Put in a word for me, will you?
好吧，我跟人事部讲讲
I'll speak to personnel
不过，你可要请吃饭
But the next lunch is on you
怎样都行
I'll
多谢你明哥
Thanks, Ming
好了，好了
It's ready
还没呢，饭熟了那个键会跳起来
No, it'll switch itself off
哪有这么快，你这乡下人
I told you, it's not ready
电饭锅啊，新买的，顾太太？
A rice cooker, It's yours, Mrs. Koo?
像我们这些老古板
No, it's beyond us
哪晓得买这种东西，是陈太太的
It's Mrs. Chan's
我先生从日本带回来的
My husband brought it from Japan
我看挺好，所以介绍给顾太太
I wanted to show Mrs. Koo how good it is
跳起来了，跳起来了
Now it's ready
这回真行了，你看多方便
It's workable, you can see
陈太太
Mrs. Chan
麻烦你陈先生，下次帮我带一个回来
Could Mr.Chan get me one next time?
好，没问题
No problem
周先生，你也应该买上一个
Mr.Chow, you should get one too
你太太老是值夜班，有了它就方便多了
Your wife's so often late home
麻烦陈先生不太好意思
I couldn't trouble Mr.Chan
隔壁邻居，无所谓啦
It's just neighborly, isn't it?
不要紧，他过两天会再去
It's no trouble
我叫他多带一个回来
I'll ask him to buy another next time
那么多谢你了
Thank you
来，我们尝尝
Let's try the rice
真不好意思，要你老远带电饭锅给我
Mr.Chan, sorry to trouble you about the rice cooker
顺手的嘛，用不着客气
It was really no trouble
还没付钱你，该多少钱？
How much do I owe you?
你太太已经给我了
Your wife has already paid me
是吗？
Really?
她没告诉你？
She didn't tell you?
她这阵子值夜班
She's been working late shifts
等她回来我已经睡了
Often I'm asleep when she gets back
在酒店做事也真辛苦
It must be hard for her
是啊
Yes
陈太太还没回来？
Mrs. Chan isn't back yet?
我想她快回来了，你有事找她？
She'll be back soon, you need to talk to her
我有个朋友过两天去新加坡
A friend needs to go to Singapore
想看看陈太太的公司有没有 便宜点的船票
I wonder if she could get a cheap ticket for him
等她回来我告诉她
I'll ask when she gets back
麻烦你们不好意思
I'm bothering you too much
客什么气，大家隔壁邻居，应该的
Don't mention it, we're neighbors
那么我先回去了
I'll leave you in peace
怎么，找我？
Looking for me?
打着锣找呢，整个上午到哪儿去了？
Damn right, where've you been?
什么事呀？
What's up?
陈太太打电话来
Mrs. Chan called
说你把帽子忘在她公司了
you left a hat at her office
我故意的，不然哪有机会多看她两眼
I meant to, I wanted an excuse to go back
早知你会来这一手
I know your tricks
人家可是有老公的
she's married
我当然知道她有老公
I know
要不我还回来干嘛
That's why I left
干脆搬到你那儿去
otherwise I'd move in next door
说真的，幸好你老婆也是美人
If your wife wasn't so attractive
要不然我可要替她担心
She'd be a worried woman
你当我是你啊
I'm not like you
帮我打电话约陈太太
Please call Mrs. Chan for me
说我明天上她公司拿帽子
I'll pick up the hat tomorrow
顺便请她喝茶
And take her to lunch
你想得美
Dream on, I asked her to
我跟她说了，把帽子先拿回家
take the hat home
明早我帮你带回来
I'll bring it in tomorrow
真泄气，还是老朋友呢
You're kidding, some buddy you are
索性我跟你回家去
Tell you what, let's go pick up now
这个钟点应该下班了
She should be off work by now
一块儿接她下班去
We can go together
懒得跟你讲
I don't have time for this
阿周
Chow
来啦，快走吧，我还要忙
Yes, get out of here, I'm busy
这样吧，我先走，在家等你
Then I'll wait at your place
就这么说定了
That's all
炳，炳
Ping
周先生，顾先生在不在？
Mr.Chow, is Mr.Koo in?
他出去了，又忘了买报纸了?
He's out, forgot to buy the paper again?
是，我待会儿再来
That's right, I'll stop by later
- 我帮你找找看 - 谢谢你
Maybe I can find it for you Thank you
- 是这一张吗？ - 是的
This one? Yes
我以前也常看的，一天不看就不自在
I always loved those serials, hated to miss an episode
是吗？你也喜欢看武侠小说？
Really? You like them too?
迷过一阵子，我还想过自己写
I even thought of writing one
为什么没写
Why didn't you?
想来想去开不了头，也就算了
I couldn't get started, so I gave up
注定不是干这一行的
I wasn't born to write martial arts stories
那些武侠小说我都留着，要看你拿去
But you can borrow from my collection any time
不了，下回再麻烦你，谢谢你
Not now, maybe another time, thanks
不客气
You're welcome
什么事，陈太太？
What is it, Mrs. Chan?
这些书还给周先生的，他在不在家？
I just want to return these to Mr.Chow is he in?
他好几天没回来
He's been away for a few days
怎么回事？
Why?
两夫妻吵架了
They had a quarrel
你把书搁下吧，等周先生回来
Leave them with me
我帮你还给他
I'll pass them back to him
谢谢
Thank you
不用了
Forget it
今晚我值夜班
I'm on a replacement shift tonight
你先回去吧
Talk to you later
再说吧，今晚我会迟一点， 你不用来接我了
No need to pick me up
她已经走啦
She's already left
是吗，还想接她一块吃夜宵
Really? I was going to take her out for supper
她没告诉你吗？她今天早下班
Didn't she tell you she was off early today
她老是这样，颠三倒四的
She never remembers to tell me
说不定已经回到家里了
Maybe she's home by now
那我先走了
I'll be off, then
好的，再见
Okay, bye
你好
Hello
你出院了吗？
You're out of hospital
先别说了，借我三十块
Don't mention hospital, Lend me $30
干什么？
What for?
帮帮忙，名誉攸关
You gotta help me save face
出了什么大事？
What's the big deal?
还不是那个阿海，那天来医院看我
It's Ah Hoi's fault
说有内幕消息，稳赢的
He gave me a racing tip, said it was a sure thing
我看他那么有把握，线都来不及拆
Before they'd taken out the stitches
一股劲跑出医院，赶去马场
I rushed from hospital to Race Course
把老婆本都押上了
I bet everything I had
结果输了个精光
and I lost my shirt
活该，刚开完刀还要去赌
What did you expect?
我想负伤上阵，必有大运
I thought it was my lucky day
谁知输剩两块钱
Anyhow, I had only $2 left
赌气就跑去找贵妃
So I went to the whorehouse
病到这样子你还要去玩女人啊？
You were in no shape for sex
想冲冲喜嘛
I thought it would improve for sex
不是只剩两块钱？够吗？
What would $2 buy you?
我是常客，好商量，先赊着也可以的
I'm Kwai Fei's regular, she gives me credit
这种事情也可以赊账？
You can have in on credit?
把身份证押给她
I left my ID card and
说好两三天后回去拿
said I'd be back to redeem it
原以为这么一点钱很容易
I thought a few dollars would be back easy to rustle up
谁知到现在还没搞定，还过了期
But so far nothing I'm way overdue
那怎办？
So?
怎办？昨儿小四上去
Four Eyes was there yesterday
可不就看见她拿着我那张身份证
Saw her waving my ID around in
到处让人看
front of everyone
你说衰不衰啊？
So embarrassing
先别说了，给我三十块
Anyway, lend me $30
我只有那么多
This is all can spare
留十块，这些你拿去用
I need $10 for myself
月初就还你
Pay you back next month
- 去吃宵夜 - 还要吃宵夜？
Let's have a late snack What?
一整天就吃了一碗云吞面，都快饿死了
All I've had today is some won-ton noodles
等我写好这一段吧
Let me finish writing this first
有件事，我不知道要不要跟你说
I'm not sure I should tell you this
什么事？
What?
昨天在街上看见你老婆
I saw your wife in the street yesterday
这有什么好奇怪的？
So what?
奇怪倒不奇怪
That is nothing
不过她好像跟一个男人走在一起
but she was with some guy
可能是她朋友
Probably a friend
说得也对，我不过是随便说说而已
Just thought you should know
余小姐吗，我是苏秘书啊
Miss Yu? This is me
何先生还在谈事情
Mr.Ho's still in a meeting
他说晚上恐怕不能跟你吃饭
he says he can't manage dinner
是，我们这阵子很忙
Yes, we're very busy now
好的，我会跟他说，再见
I'll, I'll ask Mr.Ho to call
- 你跟余小姐说了没有？ - 说过了
Have you called Miss Yu? Yes, I've
她怎么说？
What did she say?
她叫你晚一点给她电话
Asks you to call her later
何太太来过电话，说快切蛋糕了
And Mrs. Ho says she's ready to cut her birthday cake
叫你快回去
She wants you to hurry home
- 礼物买了没有？ - 买了
Did you get me something to give her? Yes, this
- 是什么东西？ - 是围巾
What is it? A scarf
- 我想何太太会喜欢吧 - 麻烦你了
I think Mrs. Ho will like it Thank you
用剩的钱
And here's your change
不用了，你拿着，老是麻烦你
I'm always troubling you
车费也要的
use it for bus fare
不如，到我家吃顿便饭？
Why don't you dine with us tonight?
别客气，我约了我先生看电影
Thank you, I've already planned to see a film tonight
那就不妨碍你们了
Then I won't keep you
明天上午没什么事
Tomorrow will be quiet
你可以下午才回来
take the morning off
- 再见 - 再见
Goodbye goodbye
你今天晚上会出去吗？
Are you going out tonight?
记得拿钥匙
Don't forget your keys
孙太太他们去吃喜酒
All the neighbors are dining out tonight
公司很忙，我会晚点回来
I have a lot to do here so I'll be late
什么事，陈太太
What is it, Mrs. Chan?
我听见隔壁有声音
I heard voices
还以为是顾先生顾太太回来
I thought Mr.& Mrs. Koo were back
还没有，你找他们有事？
Not yet, anything I can help with?
没什么，找他们聊聊天
No, I just wanted a chat
- 你一个人？ - 是
Are you alone? Yes, I am
这么早回来？
You're back early today
有点不舒服，就早点回来了
I'm not feeling well, I came back to rest
你哪里不舒服，我有药
What is it? I have some medicines
不用了，我睡会儿就好
Don't trouble yourself, I'll sleep it off
好，我不打扰了
In that case, I'll leave you in peace
你的老婆
It was your wife
跟你老婆说了没有？
Have you spoken to your wife yet?
那么你以后别再找我
Then we shouldn't meet any more
菲律宾那边有没有消息
Any news from the Philippines?
刚收到电报
Yes, a telex
说那边刮台风，船都不能开
There's a typhoon, so the ship's still docked
那么你马上通知陈先生
Please inform Chan
说他那批货可能要晚一两天才能到
That the shipment may be delayed
问他有没有问题
Ask if that's a problem
何太太打过电话来
Your wife rang
说用不着回家去接她
you don't need to pick her up
她在跟刘太太打牌
She's playing mahjong with Mrs. Lau
你五点半直接上天香楼找她便行
She'll meet you at the restaurant at 5:30
余小姐有一份礼物交给你
and there's a gift from Miss Yu
她上来过？
She was here?
不，她找人送上来的
No, she had it sent over
她说知道你今天生日，应酬多
She says she'll dine alone since it's your birthday
所以不找你吃饭了
Please phone her
叫你有空再给她电话
when you have a moment
- 我帮你倒杯咖啡 - 谢谢
I'll get you another coffee Thank you
谢谢
Thank you
领带很漂亮
That tie looks good on you
你看得出我换了领带吗？
You noticed?
我还以为差不多
It's much like the old one
仔细看能看出来
You notice things if you pay attention
我先走了
I'll be off now
如果陈先生那边有问题
If Chan has a problem
打电话到天香楼找我
let me know at the restaurant
怎么把领带又换了？
Why did you change your tie?
我嫌那条太花俏了点儿
The new one was too showy
还是换回原来的好
I should stick with my own
记得锁门啊
Don't forget to lock up
对了，最近很少看见你先生
By the way, haven't seen your husband lately
是呀，这阵子他公司有事，派了他出去
He's abroad now, on company business
怪不得老在面摊碰见你
That's why I see you at the noodle stall
一个人懒得煮饭
I don't like cooking for myself
对了，你太太呢？最近也很少看见她
Haven't seen your wife lately either
她妈妈身体不太舒服，回娘家陪陪她
Her mother's ill, she's at home with her
难怪了
That explains it
- 晚安 - 晚安
Good night Good night
陈太太，你回来就好了
Mrs. Chan, I'm glad you're back
外面雨下得那么凶
It's raining so hard
我还想打伞去接你呢
I was going to look for you with and umbrella
不过是阵头雨，你有心
You are too kind
王妈，是谁？
Amah, who is it?
是陈太太
It's Mrs. Chan
孙太太
Mrs. Suen
哎呀，下那么大雨还出去呀
Caught in the rain? I said you could
大家自己人，早叫你一道吃
eat with us
下回吧，慢慢打
Next time, Enjoy your game
哎呀，她先生一天到晚在外头
Her husband's always away
她一个人孤伶伶怪可怜的
It's sad to see her to lonely
出去买碗面，还穿得真漂亮
She dresses up like that to go out for noodle
周先生，怎么到这边来了？
Mr.Chow, What are you doing here?
我过来叫顾太太听电话
Just calling Mrs. Koo to the phone
这么晚？
You're late back
刚看了场电影
I went to the picture
我先回去了
I'll be going
喂
Hello
啊，你等等啊
Yes, please hold on
- 是谁的电话？ - 陈太太的电话
Who is it? It's for Mrs. Chan
那么冒昧约你出来，是有点事想请教你
It must seem odd to ask you out but I want to ask something
你今天下午拿着的皮包
That handbag I saw you with this evening
不知道哪里有的买？
Where did you buy it?
你为什么这样问？
Why do you ask?
哦，我看款式很别致
It looked so elegant
想买一个送给我太太
I want to get one for my wife
周先生对太太真细心
Mr.Chow, you're so good to your wife
那里，她这人很挑剔
Not really, my wife is so fussy
过两天她生日
Her birthday is two days away
不知道买什么送给她才好
I don't know what to get her
你可不可以帮我买一个？
Could you buy one for me to give her?
要是一模一样的，她会不喜欢吧
Maybe she wouldn't want one just exactly the same
说的也是，我倒也没想到
You're right, I didn't think of that
女人会介意，对吧？
Women would mind
会的，特别是隔壁邻居
Yes, especially since we're neighbors
不知道会不会有别的颜色
Do they come in other colors?
那要问我先生才知道
I'd have to ask my husband
为什么？
Why?
那皮包是我先生
He bought it for me
在外地工作的时候买给我的
on a business trip abroad
他说在香港没有卖的
They aren't on sale here
那就算了吧
Then never mind
其实
Actually
我也有一件事情想请教你
I want to ask your something too
什么事？
What?
你的领带在哪里买的？
Where did you buy your tie?
我还真的不知道
I don't know where it came from
我领带全是我太太帮我买的
My wife buys all my ties
是吗？
Really?
我想起来了，有一次她公司派她出去
She bought this one
回来送给我的
on a business trip abroad
她说香港没有卖的
It's not on sale here
倒有这么巧
What a coincidence
是啊
Yes
其实
Actually
我先生也有条领带跟你的一模一样
My husband has one just like it
他说是他老板送他的
He said it was a gift from his boss
所以天天戴着
So he wears it every day
我太太也有个皮包跟你那个一模一样
Any my wife has a bag just like yours
我知道，我见过
I know, I have seen it
你想说什么
What are you getting at, actually?
我还以为只有我一个人知道
I thought I was the only one who knew
不知道他们是怎样开始的
I wonder how it began
你这么晚不回家，你老婆不说你吗？
It's late, won't your wife complain?
早习惯了，她不管我的
She's used to it, she doesn't care
你呢？你老公不说什么吗？
And your husband?
我想他早睡了
He must be asleep by now
今晚别回去了
Shall we stay out tonight?
我老公不会这样讲的
My husband would never say that
他会怎么讲
What would he say?
就是不会讲
Anyhow, he wouldn't say that
总有一个人先开口吧
Someone must have made the first move
不是他是谁？
Who else could it be?
你这么晚不回家，你老婆不会问吗？
It's late, won't your wife complain?
早习惯了，她不管的
She's used to it, she doesn't care
你老公不会说什么吗？
And your husband?
我想他早睡了
He must be asleep by now
我真的说不出口
I can't say it
我明白
I understand
事到如今
After all, it's already happened
谁先开口有什么所谓
It doesn't matter who made the first move
其实你知不知道你老婆是怎样的人
Do you really know your wife?
你帮我点
You order for me
为什么？
Why?
我想知道你老婆喜欢吃什么
I've no idea what your wife likes
那么你丈夫喜欢吃什么
What about your husband?
吃得惯吗？
Like it hot?
你老婆挺能吃辣的
Your wife likes hot dishes
为什么打电话到我公司？
Why did you call me at the office today?
没事做，想听听你的声音
I had nothing to do, I want to hear your voice
学得倒挺像我老公
You have my husband down pat
油嘴滑舌
He's real sweet-talker
你为什么不打电话给我？
Why didn't you call me today?
怕你会不高兴
I was afraid you won't like it
那么以后不要再打电话给我
Then don't call me again
陈太太，陈先生有封信来了，你看看
Mrs. Chan, a letter from your husband
不是我的，是隔壁周先生的
It's not for me, it's for Mr.Chow next door
我看见信封上的日本邮票
The Japanese stamp made me think
以为是陈先生寄来
it was your husband
原来不是
So I was wrong
你老婆去了日本？
Your wife's in Japan?
你怎么知道
How did you know?
信里写些什么？
What did she say in her letter?
没什么
Nothing special
有没有说几时回来？
Anything about when she'd be back?
没有
No
你猜他们现在在做什么？
What do you think they're doing right now?
- 你没事吧？ - 没事
Are you alright? I'm fine
麻烦你在前面停停车
Please pull up here
干什么？
Why?
我先下车
I'll get off first
不好，我先下
No, let me
- 陈太太 - 炳哥，你回来了？
Mrs. Chan Ah Ping, you're back
- 是啊 - 找周先生？
Visiting Mr.Chow?
想找他喝茶，哪知道他病了
Yes, I thought we'd have lunch but he isn't well
怎么回事？
What's wrong with him?
发烧，他老婆又不在家
He's got fever, he's all alone
一个人怪可怜的，下去给他买点什么吃
So I'm gonna buy him something to eat
街口那家店，卖的粥挺好的
The congee downstairs is quite good
他不想吃粥
He doesn't want congee
他想吃什么
What does he want?
他说嘴里淡得慌，想吃芝麻糊
Can't taste anything, so he wants sesame syrup
真难缠
Damned troublesome
王妈，王妈
Amah
孙太太，王妈上天台晾衣服去了
Mrs. Suen, she's hanging the washing on the roof
你回来了
You're back
这是刚上街回来？
Yes, you've been out?
是呀，下礼拜我妈过生日
My mother's birthday is coming up
我带她去买点布料做新衣
So I took her to buy some fabric
跑了一整天，气都喘不上来了
It took all day, I'm half dead
顺道烫了个头发，好看吗？
And I had my hair done, is it nice?
很漂亮
Very nice
你在煮什么？
What are you cooking?
忽然想吃芝麻糊
I had a sudden craving for sesame syrup
一大锅你怎么吃呀
That whole pot is for you
反正煮了，大家一块吃吧
I thought I might as well make a potful
你真客气
You're so thoughtful
- 来一碗吧 - 好啊
Please try it I'll
这么巧
What a coincidence
是啊，上街吗？
Going out?
整晚没吃过东西了，下来吃碗面
I'll buy some noodles, I'm starving
你饿不饿？一起啊？
Hungary? Will you join me?
不了
No thanks
这么晚才下班？
Just off work?
公司很忙？
You must be very busy
就是没事做，所以看了场电影
Actually, I've been to see a picture
是吗，好不好看？
Really? How was it?
马马虎虎
So-so
我从前也爱看电影
I used to like going to the pictures
你以前倒是挺多嗜好的
You had many hobbies before
自己一个人，大把时间， 想做什么就做什么
On your own, you are free to do lots of things
结了婚就不一样
Everything changes when you marry
很多事情，一个人作不了主
It must be decided together
对不对？
Right?
有时候我会想，要是现在还没有结婚
I sometimes wonder what I'd be
不知会怎样
if I hadn't married
你也会这样想吗？
Have you ever thought of that?
可能会比较开心吧
Maybe happier
我以前都没有想到婚姻
I didn't know married life would be
是这样复杂
so complicated
如果一个人，自己做得好就够了
When you're single, you are only responsible to yourself
可是当两个人在一起时
Once you're married
只有自己做得好是不够的
doing well on your own is not enough
别想太多了，等他们回来再说吧
Don't brood on it, maybe he'll be back soon
你没事啊？
What about you?
其实我跟你还不是一样
Actually, we're in the same boat
我只是不去想
But I don't brood on it
又不是我做错
It's not my fault
何必每天问自己做错了什么
I can't waste time wondering if I made mistakes
浪费自己时间
Life's too short for that
我不想这样下去
Something must change
你有什么打算？
So what's your plan?
这几天我躺在床上翻武侠小说
I want to write a martial-arts
我想再写
serial...
已经开了头，过两天让你看
Actually, I've started one, I'll show it to you
好啊
Great
你这么喜欢看武侠小说
You like them too
我们一起写吧
so why not help me write it?
这怎么行，我只会看，哪里会写
I wouldn't know how, I only read them
试试看嘛
We would discuss it together
那好吧，我尽量
Alright, I'll try my best
还没多谢你的芝麻糊呢
I never thanked you for the sesame syrup
别客气，小意思嘛
There's no need I was making it anyway
说起来真巧
Amazing, I was craving for some
刚好那天我很想吃芝麻糊
sesame syrup that day
是吗，这么巧
Really? What's a coincidence
是呀，就这么巧
It really was
我先去吃点东西
I'll go for those noodles
老是这样子，酒席吃到一半就醉倒
Again, halfway through dinner, he's drunk
真讨厌
Disgusting
- 早说别给他喝了 - 我有啥办法
- I told you to stop - What can you do?
是我
It's me
吓死我了
You scared me
怎样？顾先生有没有事？
How's Mr.Koo?
喝醉了吧
Drunk, as usual
怎会这样早
I didn't expect them back so early
反正没法子，不如先把面吃完再说
Since you're trapped here, finish the noodles
我想他们坐一会儿就走
They'll probably go soon
加点汤吗？
Want some soup?
要不要加点汤？
孙太太，怎么在这边打麻将？
Mrs. Suen, playing here tonight
顾太太说要看着她先生嘛
Yes, Mrs. Koo is dealing with her husband
早跟我说嘛，我来照顾他就行了
I could do that
怎好意思呀
No, we should not trouble you
这样高兴，看来要玩到天亮
Think you'll play all night?
才不会，顶多八圈
No, we'll just play eight rounds
你猜他们会不会打到天亮？
They'll play till morning?
孙太太说只打八圈
Mrs. Suen says only eight rounds
你信不信？
You believe that?
不如你瞌睡一会，他们散了我就叫你
You get some rest, I'll wake you when they leave
那你呢？
And you?
我先把这段写好
I have a chapter to finish
写到哪儿？
Where have you got to?
大醉侠出场
The drunken master just showed up
怎么多了个大醉侠？
When did he get written in?
刚想到的
Just now
周先生，这样早就出去啊
Mr.Chow, home so early?
我下去买点吃的
I went out to buy some food
你今天不用上班吗？
No work today?
有点不太舒服，告了一天假
I didn't feel so good, I'm staying home
不舒服还吃这么多糯米鸡
A sick man shouldn't eat all that sticky rice
省得晚上再出去买
Some of it's for later
当心吃撑了
Don't stuff yourself
周先生
Good morning
你早，散场了吗，孙太太？
Good morning, finished your game?
没有呢，杨先生要办公，让他先走了
Not yet, but Mr.Yang has to work
不过蔡先生马上就来
Mr.Tsai is coming to replace him
有没有帮我打电话回公司请假？
Did you call the office for me?
打过了
Yes
你怎么说的
What did you tell them?
说你病了
That you weren't feeling well
他们有没有问你是谁
Did them ask who you were?
没有
No
多半以为我是你丈夫吧
Probably took me for your husband
何先生知道他出门了
Mr.Ho knows that he's away
就说他已经回来好了
Pretend he's come back
都是自己吓自己
Maybe we're being too cautious?
平日我也常过来
I'm always round anyway
有什么好紧张的
We shouldn't have panicked
这很难说，他们突然之间回来
Well, they did turn up without warning
不知道他们会怎么乱想
What would they assume?
所以真的不能走错一步
We can't put a foot wrong
走吧
You can go
- 王妈 - 陈太太，怎么这样晚？
Amah Mrs. Chan, you're back very late
是呀，今天公司事情多
I had a lot of work today
怎么今早没看见你上班？
I didn't see you leave this morning
今天很早约了妈妈喝茶
I had breakfast with my mother
我出去的时候你还没来
You weren't here when I left
孙太太呢？
Where's Mrs. Suen?
她搓麻将搓到天亮，才刚睡
Asleep, she played mahjong all day
- 别吵她了 - 好的
Be quiet, don't wake her Alright
呀，陈太太，你的脚还好吧
Mrs. Chan, is your leg alright?
没什么，新鞋子太窄，挤脚了
It's these new shoes
干嘛请我吃饭？
Why a special dinner tonight?
今天出稿费，你那一份你又不收
Since you won't take your share of
只好请你吃饭了
the writing fee
其实不关我的事
None of my business
我在旁边打打边鼓而已
All I did was give you some thoughts
我也许会多写一家报纸
Someone else is asking for a serial too
今天有人打电话来约稿
There'll be more work soon
是吗？那太好了
Really? So quickly
你应付得了吗？
Isn't the workload too much?
所以想找一个地方
That's why I'm looking for a new place
做什么？
What for?
写东西
To write in
这样你以后上来都方便点嘛
lt'll be more convenient
虽然我们之间没什么
There's nothing between us
但是我不想别人误会你
but I don't want gossip
你觉得怎样？
What do you think?
太浪费了
Why waste money?
其实都是你自己写的
You don't need me
何必多此一举呢
you can write on your own
喂，找谁呀？
Who do you want?
周慕云？
Chow Mo-Wan?
他没上班好几天了
He hasn't been in for several days
我们也到处在找他
We're looking for him too
你是哪位啊？
May I know who's calling?
要留个话吗？
Any message?
哦，不用谢，多挂来啊
It's no trouble, goodbye
这文件马上送去会计部
Please get this to Accounts
还有，冷气机明天叫人来看看
And have the air-conditioner serviced tomorrow
好，何先生
Mr.Ho
没什么事了，你可以走了
No need to stay if everything's done
- 门我来锁喽 - 好的
I'll lock up Yes
喂
Hello?
你在哪里啊？
Where are you?
我明天再来看你
I'll come again tomorrow
我歇两天就没事
No need, I'll be alright after some rest
不要紧，才一会儿功夫
It's no trouble
我给你买点吃的，你想吃什么
I'll bring you some food, what would you like?
随便
Whatever
那我就走了，你早点休息
Then I'll leave now, get some rest
回去给我个电话
Call me when you get home
用不着说话，响三声就好
Let it ring three times then hang up
好
Alright
我没想过你会来
I didn't think you'd come
我们不会跟他们一样的
We won't be like them
明天见
See you tomorrow
你老实告诉我
Tell me honestly
你外面是不是有个女人？
Do you have a mistress?
神经病
You're crazy
谁跟你说的
Who told you I had?
你别管
Never mind who
你是不是有了个女人
Do you or don't you?
没有
No
不要骗我
Don't lie
你看着我，你看着我
Look at me
我问你，你外面是不是有个女人？
I'm asking you, do you have a mistress
是
Yes
你怎么了？
That's no reaction
他已经承认在外面有个女人
If he admits it outright
你还打得这么轻
let him have it
我没想到他会回答得这样干脆
I wasn't expecting he would admit it so easily
我不知道该怎么办
I didn't know how to react
再来一次吧
One more time, alright?
你老实回答我
Tell me frankly
你外面是不是有个女人？
Do you have a mistress?
神经病
You're crazy
谁跟你说的？
Who told you that?
你别管，你是不是有个女人？
Never mind that, do you or don't you?
没有
No
你不要骗我
Don't lie
你告诉我
Tell me
你看着我，是不是有个女人？
Look at me, do you have a mistress?
是
Yes
你没事吧
Are you alright?
我没想到真的会这样伤心
I didn't expect it to hurt so much
我试试而已，又不是真的
This is just a rehearsal
就算是真的他也不会认
He won't really admit it so readily
没事的，别这样
It's alright, don't take it so hard
你最近好像应酬挺多的？
You've been out a lot lately
是啊
Yes
年纪轻呢，出去散散心是应该的
It's right to enjoy yourself while you're young
不过得有分寸
But don't overdo it
你先生几时回来？
When will your husband be back?
他快回来了
Soon
等他回来呢，别再让他老出门
In future, don't let him travel so much
两夫妻经常分开呢，总不大好
A couple should spend time together
你说对吗？
Don't you agree?
晚安
Good night
你今天晚上过不过来？
Will you come over tonight?
做什么？
What for?
这两天给催稿，说我写得慢
The editor's hounding me, he says I'm too slow
过来帮忙手啊？你几点可以？
I need your help, when can you come?
我想这阵子我不过来了
Not anytime soon
怎么了？
Why not?
昨晚回家，让孙太太说了几句
Mrs. Suen lectured me last night
她说你什么
What did he say?
我不想讲
Rather not say
反正这阵子我们还是少点见面吧
We shouldn't see so much of each other
陈太太，又要去买面啊？
Mrs. Chan, going out for noodles again?
今天不去了
Not tonight, I'll make myself something
随便弄点什么吃的就算了
Join us, we're having vegetable won-tons
那好的
Alright
- 何先生没出去吃午饭？ - 没有
- No lunch today, Mr.Ho? - No
刚才有位周先生打电话找你
Now one Mr.Zhou call you
叫你回电话给他
He wants you to call him back
谢谢
Thank you
- 下班啦？ - 是呀
- Back from work? - Yes
- 这真是大雨呀 - 是呀
- Strange weather Isn't it - Yes
在这儿站很久了？
Been here long?
一会儿罢了
Just a while
我想还得下好一会儿
I don't think it'll stop soon
你等等我
Wait for me
我送你回去
I'll see you home
让人看见，又话多了
We'd better not be seen together
那么你先回去
Then you go first
他们认得你的伞
If they see your umbrella
我撑着回去，不也一样？
They'll know I was with you
这也是，我倒没想到
I wasn't thinking
你先回去吧，我待一会儿就回
You go first, I'll wait a while
我陪你
I'll keep you company
你找过我？
Did you try to call me?
还以为你同事忘了告诉你
I wasn't sure you got the message
想找你买张船票
Could you get me a boat ticker?
你要去别的地方？
To where?
阿炳来过很多信
Ah Ping wrote from Singapore
说那边缺人手，要我去帮他忙
They're short of staff, he'd like me to go and help
打算去多久？
How long will you stay?
不知道，去了再说吧
Don't know, I'll play it be ear
怎么突然会想去新加坡？
Why rush off to Singapore?
想换―下环境
A change of scene...
免得听着太多的闲言闲语
I've had enough of the gossip
我们自己知道我们没什么不就行了
We know it's not true, so why worry?
原来我也这样想
I used to think that too
所以不怕别人说闲话
and it didn't worry me
我相信我自己不会像他们那样
I thought we wouldn't be like them
原来会的
But I was wrong
我知道你不会离开你丈夫
You won't leave your husband
我想离开一下
So I'd rather go away
我没有想过你真的会喜欢我
I didn't think you'd fall in love with me
我也没有想过
I didn't either
我一直在想，他们是怎样开始的
I was only curious to know how it started
现在我明白了
Now I know
原来很多事情都这样
Feelings can creep up just like that
我还以为自己没有什么
I thought I was in control
但是开始担心你丈夫几时会回来
But I hate to think of our husband coming home
最好不要回来
I wish he'd stay away
我知道这样想不对
I'm so bad
你能不能帮我一个忙
Will you do me one favour?
做什么？
What?
我想有点心理准备
I want to be prepared
以后不要再找我了
You'd better not see me again
你老公他回来了？
Is your husband back?
是啊
Yes
我真没用
Am I hopeless?
不是啊
Not really
我不会再找你了
I won't see you again
好好地守着你的丈夫
Keep a closer eye on your husband
别这样
Please
说了试着的嘛
Don't be serious it's only a rehearsal
别哭
Don't cry
这又不是真的
This isn't real
我今天晚上不想回家
I don't want to go home tonight
陈美仪点给好朋友权仔和文文
Mei-Yi wants to dedicate a song
祝他们成功
to her honeymooning friends
又点给同屋的张太太收听
And Mrs. Cheung wishes the best to
祝家庭幸福
her neighbors
有一位在日本公干的陈先生
And Mr.Chan, now on business in Japan
点这首歌给他太太
wants to wish his wife
祝她生日快乐，工作顺利
a happy birthday
现在请大家一起欣赏，周璇唱的
So let's all enjoy Zhou Xuan singing
花样的年华
In Full Bloom
是我
It's me
如果有多一张船票
If there's an extra ticket
你会不会跟我一起走？
Would you go with me?
是我
It's me
如果有多一张船票
If there's an extra ticket
你会不会带我一起走？
Would you go with me?
哈罗？周先生不在，他上班去了
Mr.Chow has gone to work
有话要转达吗？
Any message?
不用谢，拜拜
You're welcome
是不是有人进过我房间？
Has anyone been in my room?
没有呀
No
没有？我丢了东西
Something's missing
丢了什么呀
What?
你知不知道，从前的人
In the old days
要是心里有了秘密，不想别人知道
If someone had a secret they didn't want to share
你知不知道他们会怎样做？
You know what they did?
我怎么知道？
Have no idea
他们会跑到山上找一棵树
They went up to a mountain, found a tree
在树上挖个洞
Carved a hole in it
然后把秘密全说进去
And whispered the secret into the hole
再用泥巴封起来
Then they covered it with mud
那秘密就永远留在那棵树里，没人知道
And leave the secret there forever
这样辛苦，找个女人发泄一下不更好
What a pain, I'd just go to get laid
谁都像你呀
Not everyone's like you
说得是呀，像我这样的人
I'm just an average guy
是个直肠子，哪来的心事呀？
I don't have secrets like you
你可不同，什么都往心里搁
You bottle things up
说来听听嘛
Tell me something
我哪有心事
I don't have secrets
你别瞒我啦，一场朋友
Come off it, buddy
我不会跟别人说的
I won't tell anyone
喂，你好，星洲日报
Hello, Singapore Daily
请等等
Hold on
云哥，电话
Mr.Chow, call for you
谢谢
Thanks
喂
Hello
- 谁呀？ - 王妈，是我啊
- Who is it? - It is me
- 陈太太，好久没见了 - 是呀
- Mrs. Chan, long time no see - Yes
- 王妈，什么人呀 - 孙太太
- Amah, who's there? - Mrs. Suen
哎呀，你怎么会过来啊？
What brings you here?
我想这么久没来看你
It's been a while
今天刚好来这附近
I was nearby
特意把船票给你送来
so I thought I'd bring your boat ticket
请你吃的
And a small gift
哎呀，上来坐坐就好了， 还这样客气，又破费
You shouldn't have, it's nice just to see you
你看这屋里乱七八糟的
The place is in such a mess
你已经在收拾了？
Already started packing?
已经收拾好几天了
It's hopeless,
东西太多，有些又舍不得扔
I can't bear to throw things away
- 坐的地方都没有，到这边坐 - 好啊
- Let's find you a seat - OK
- 吃茶 - 谢谢，王妈
- Have some tea - Thank you
你今天别走，在这里吃晚饭，我去买菜
Eat with us, Mrs. Chan, I'm going to the market
不行呢，我还得回公司办点事
I can't, I have work waiting
你干嘛急着走
Don't rush off
你不留在这儿吃饭
if you don't eat here
太太要不高兴的，太太？
Mrs. Suen will be upset
嗳，你替我倒杯茶来
Amah, pour me some tea too
陈先生好吗？
How's your husband?
挺好的，有心了
He's fine, thank you
你打算走多久？
How long will you be away?
我也不晓得
I don't know
要是住的惯呢我就不回来了
If I like it, I might stay
为什么？
Why?
我女儿说现在香港这么乱
My daughter worries about the situation in Hong Kong
我自己一个人在这边她不放心
She worry about I stay alone in Hong Kong
我倒是舍不得离开香港的
I don't want to leave
不过自从顾先生他们搬走了以后
Since the Koos left
搓麻将也没搭伴
I don't have my mahjong partners anymore
想想呢，还是到美国去给女儿带孩子算了
And my daughter needs help with her kids in the US
这房子怎么办？
What about this place?
正为了这个伤脑筋嘛
I'm not sure
卖出去呢真不舍得
I don't want to sell it
想想还是租给人家吧
So I might rent it out
你打算租多少钱？
How much would you want?
嗳？你有意思租吗？
You're interested?
租给你我可就放心了， 我便宜点租给你啦
You could have it at a discount
我想想看
I'll think about it
太太，吃茶
Mrs. Suen, your tea
对了，现在是什么人住在隔壁？
Who lives next door now?
我也不大晓得，不像以前，都没往来
I don't really know them
以前跟顾先生顾太太不知多热闹
The Koos were almost like family
像一家人一样，想起来也开心
It was so nice then
你说是吗？
wasn't it?
是啊
Yes
过来这边坐
Let's sit over here
你找哪位？
Yes?
请问顾先生在不在？
Is Mr.Koo in?
顾先生？搬了好久了
He moved long ago
知不知道搬到哪儿去了？
Do you know where he is?
你跟他很熟吗？
You know him well?
我从前住在这里
I used to live here
孙太太还住在隔壁吗？
Is Mrs. Suen still next door?
也搬了，现在乱成这样
She's gone, it's too chaotic
能走的还不走吗？
Everyone's running away
现在隔壁住着什么人？
So who lives there now?
我也不太清楚
I am not sure
好像就是一个女人带着她儿子
A woman and her son
那小孩子蛮可爱的
The kid is cute
他菲律宾的地址我没找着
No address in the Philippines
只有他儿子的电话
Just his son's phone number
- 你拿回去 - 这怎行
- I can't accept this - How this
小意思，不客气
Please, you must
- 那么谢谢了 - 慢走
- Thank you, then - Bye
那个时代已过去
That era has passed
属于那个时代的一切
Nothing that belonged to
都不存在了
it exists any more
庸生，好了没？
Are you ready?
- 好了 - 快点
- Okay - Let's go
柬埔寨首都机场上
The presidential corps waits at Pochentong Airport
皇室人员上前
Prince Norodom Sihanouk and Queen sisowath Kossamak
迎接戴高乐将军
come forward to greet General De Gaulle
公路上列队欢迎
It's ten kilometres from Pochentong to Phnom Penh
人潮达二十万人
200,000 people line the route
写下该国前所未有的一页
A welcome unprecedented in the history of the Kingdom